Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitap-i Cerrahname] Uniform title: Cerrahname Title (English): [This is the book of Surgery] Alternative titles: ????? ????, Jarrah'namah, Kitabü'l-cerrahiyei ilhaniye, Date: no date; Manuscript number: 307; 109 leaves: paper; 220 x 159 mm. bound to 210 x 158 mm.; Layout: 
  Identified following DP. But Kâtip Çelebi identifies another such title composed by a certain Ibrahim b. Abdullah Cerrah [Under jim, Ilm al- jira?ah].
  Medical text, if correctly identified, a translation from a Mongol period Persian original.
- Title (Romanized): [Ferâiz tercümesi] Title (English): [Translation of inheritance law], Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 308; 110 leaves: paper; 214 x 155 mm. bound to 213 x 156 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 68)
- Title (Romanized): Bostan-i kuds ve gülistan-i üns Title (English): [The orchard of sanctity and the rose garden and intimacy] Alternative titles: Bostân-i kudsî ve gülistân-i ünsî, Bustan Quds wa Gulistan-i Uns, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 309; 255 leaves: paper; 206 x 145 mm. bound to 212 x 154 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black cloth with red leather stripe over spine and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the end. (Box 68)
  Form of author's name as wel as his death date from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 416, but the author notes that he had begun the work in 1591, and it seems unlikely that he lived another 70 years after that.
  An exposition on religious matters with ample stories and references to the hadith and the Koran.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Sebiyyat Title (English): [Translation of] the Septets Alternative titles: ????? ??????? Tarjumah al-Sab'iyat fi mawa'i? al-barriyat, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 310; 251 leaves: paper; 208 x 143 mm. bound to 200 x 140 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather with black leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage. (Box 68)
  A Turkish translation of al- Sab'iyat fi mawa'i? al-barriyat originally composed in Arabic by 'Ayn al-Qu?ah, Mu?ammad ibn 'Abd Ra?man, 16th cent. regarding the days of the week and their religious importance (supported by Koranic stories). This may or may not be the Turkish version attributed by Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al-?unun to a certain Mehmet Hilali Kad?, entitled Meclisara (Majlis'ara), completed in 1588. The manuscript contains two other titles.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i Sehname-i Rüstem] Title (English): [The translation of Rustam's Book of Kings] Alternative titles: ????? ??? ???? ????, Tarjumah-i Shah'namah-i Rustam, Date: 1761; Manuscript number: 311; 398 leaves: paper; 212 x 144 mm. bound to 212 x 145 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded soft blak leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 68)
  Prose Turkish translation of the Shah'namah of Firdawsi, starting with Kiyumarth, but mostly focued on the adventures of Rustam.
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitap-i Cebbâr Kulu] Title (English): [This is the book of Cebbâr Kulu] Alternative titles: ??? ???? ????? ???, Date: 1666 July; Manuscript number: 312; 224 leaves: paper; 230 x 165 mm. bound to 230 x 168 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded brown leather with black leather stripe over spine and edges, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, some water damage. (Box 68)
  A Sufi (Bektasi/Uveysi) biography of a certain Seyh Seyyid Ali Veysü'l-K?rani. The manuscript contains a second title.
- Title (Romanized): [Dîvân] Title (English): [Poetic anthology], Date: No date; Manuscript number: 313; 36 leaves: paper; 230 x 135 mm. bound to 238 x 140 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 68)
  Selected poems of Kaygusuz Abdal (15th cent.), and Osmanzade Taip, Ahmet (1660?-1724). Leaves are variously numbered. Blank pages separating the works of the two authors.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan-i Cahidi] Title (English): [cahidi's poetic anthology], Date: [Late 18--]; Manuscript number: 314; 69 leaves: paper; 221 x 178 mm. bound to 228 x 182 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 69)
  Poetic anthology of a poet who refers to himself as Cahidi. Incipit: Tecellidir bu ashab?n hayat?…
- Title (Romanized): [Tecdid-i harem-i mahbub-i yezdan der ahd-i Sultan Abdülmecid Han] Uniform title: Mir'at ül-haremeyn[?] Title (English): [The renovation of the beloved sanctuary of God in the days of Sultan Abdülmecid] Alternative titles: ????? ??? ????? ????? ?? ??? ????? ??? ?????? ???, Tajdid-i ?aram-i ma?bub-i yazdan dar a?d-i sul?ab Abd al-Majid Khan, Date: 1878 April; Manuscript number: 315; 12 leaves: paper; 256 x 173 mm. bound to 255 x 174 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Red leather with gilt decoration, and blue paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 69)
  An account of renovation work done on the sancuary at Mecca during the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Abdülmecid (18391861).
- Title (Romanized): Dürretü't-taç Uniform title: Dürret üt-taç Title (English): Pearl of the crown Alternative titles: ??? ?????, Dürret üt- taç fi sahib-ül miraç, Durrat al-taj, Date: 1734 December; Manuscript number: 316; 203 leaves: paper; 251 x 145 mm. bound to 252 x 152 mm.; Layout: 20 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and marble paste-down.. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b and 108b illuminated. (Box 69)
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitap-i Tutiname] Title (English): [The is the book of the parrot] Alternative titles: ???? ????, Tuti'namah, Date: 1824 November; Manuscript number: 317; 114 leaves: paper; 237 x 165 mm. bound to 235 x 165 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faded black leather with yellow and black paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 69)
  A Turkish prose work, apparently a translation of an original work of popular fables by Nakhshabi (Ziya' al-Din, d. 1350).
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitap-i Hasimname] Title (English): [This is the book of Hashim] Alternative titles: ???? ????, Hashim'namah, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 318; 168 leaves: paper; 201 x 143 mm. bound to 203 x 148 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, badly frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 69)
  A legendary/epic account of Hashim, supposedly from the early Islamic period. The original composition is attributed to the time of Sultan Mahmud of Ghazna.
- Title (Romanized): [Hamse-i Atai] Title (English): [The Quintet of `Ata'i], Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 319; 247 leaves: paper; 214 x 110 mm. bound to 211 x 107 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, gilt-inlaid, with pink marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders, 1b illuminated. (Box 69)
  Four out of the five poetic narratives of `Ata'i collected together.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan-i Subhi] Title (English): [The poetic anthology of Subhi], Date: No date; Manuscript number: 320; 9 leaves: paper; 210 x 148 mm. bound to 215 x 155 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Diwani/Nastál?q. Binding: Faux brown Morocco. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 69)
  For of name mostly from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 381.
  Selected poems of Subhi.
- Title (Romanized): [Macmua-i siir] Title (English): [Collection of poetry], Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 321; 183 leaves: paper; 199 x 133 mm. bound to 258 x 139 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Faux purple leather, with purple paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, marginalia. (Box 69)
  Collection of Ottoman Turkish poetry by Hayâlî, Ahmed Pasa, Kemâl Pasazâde, Ahi, Atai, Ahi Baba, Sururi, Riyazi, etc.
- Title (Romanized): [Macmua-i siir] Title (English): [Collection of poetry], Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 322; 60 leaves: paper; 215 x 147 mm. bound to 215 x 147 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red leather, gilt decoration around the edges, marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 69)
  Collection of Ottoman Turkish poetry, including panegyrics addressed to the Ottoman Sultans Suleyman, Mustafa and Murad (III?), by Hayâlî, Latifi, Kemâl Pasazâde, Necati, Nezmi, etc.
- Title (Romanized): [Yûsuf ve Züleyhâ] Uniform title: Yusuf ve Züleyha Title (English): [Joseph and Zulaykha] Alternative titles: Hamdu'llah Hamdi'nin Yusuf ve Züleiha mesnevisi, Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 323; 178 leaves: paper; 200 x 150 mm. bound to 201 x 148 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Decorated brown paper, with frayed leather stripe over spine; separating. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, final leaves missing. (Box 70)
  The author refers to himself and to his father Seyh Semsettin (Aksemseddin).
- Title (Romanized): [Divan-i Sebzi] Title (English): [The poetic anthology of Sebzi], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 324; 104 leaves: paper; 2060 x 145 mm. bound to 205 x 150 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Red leather, gilt decoration around the edges, marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 70)
  See Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 350.
  The poetic anthology of the Ottoman poet Sebzi Mehmet Efendi, d. 1680.
- Title (Romanized): [Yûsuf ve Züleyhâ] Uniform title: Yusuf ve Züleyha Title (English): [Joseph and Zulaykha] Alternative titles: Hamdu'llah Hamdi'nin Yusuf ve Züleiha mesnevisi, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 325; 177 leaves: paper; 178 x 118 mm. bound to 178 x 121 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Dark brown leather, blind-stamped (front board), and light brown leather (back board), with burgundy stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, final leaves rewritten later, end is missing. (Box 70)
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 326; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 70)
- Title (Romanized): [Divan-i Süruri] Title (English): [The poetic anthology of Süruri], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 327; 116 leaves: paper; 196 x 134 mm. bound to 195 x 132 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Red leather, blind-stamped and gilt, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, some water damage. (Box 70)
  The poems of Süruri collected by the author himself.
- Title (Romanized): [Acay?bü'l-mahlûkat ve garay?bü'l-masnuat] Title (English): [Wonders of creation and the strange things of invention], Date: 1659; Manuscript number: 328; 157 leaves: paper; 190 x 128 mm. bound to 190 x 128 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with marble paste-down, and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 70)
  Treatise on the wonders of the universe in sixteen chapters. Perhaps the work of Ahmet Bican, 15th cent. There is a short treatise attached to the end.
- Title (Romanized): [Yûsuf ve Züleyhâ] Uniform title: Yusuf ve Züleyha Title (English): [Joseph and Zulaykha] Alternative titles: Hamdu'llah Hamdi'nin Yusuf ve Züleiha mesnevisi, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 329; 171 leaves: paper; 209 x 127 mm. bound to 201 x 125 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Frayed green cloth over boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated; water damage; ending missing. (Box 70)
- Title (Romanized): [Münseat-i Nabi] Title (English): [The correspondence of Nabi] Alternative titles: ????? ????, Munsha'at-i Nabi, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 330; 146 leaves: paper; 208 x 147 mm. bound to 204 x 144 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green marble paper over boards with leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, marginalia. (Box 70)
  Epistolary collection of the Ottoman man of letters Nabi.
- Title (Romanized): [Icmal-i Avrupa] Title (English): [Synopsis of Europe] Alternative titles: ????? ??????, Date: [18--]?; Manuscript number: 331; 35 leaves: paper; 212 x 138 mm. bound to 210 x 142 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Green marble paper over boards with leather stripe over spine, fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders, 1b illuminated. (Box 71)
  A brief description of European countries and principalities such as Corinthia, Austria, Westphalia, Bohemia, Leon, Arragonia, Catalonia, etc.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i] Sehname Title (English): [Translation of] The Book of Kings Alternative titles: Shahnamah, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 332; 327 leaves: paper; 193 x 131 mm. bound to 203 x 140 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Blue Morocco with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders, 1b illuminated. (Box 71)
  The author calls himself the story-teller of Ottoman Sultans since the time of Murad III (r. 15741595), composing such works as Süleymanname, Edipname, Gersaspname, Maariçü'n-nübüvve, etc.
  A translation of Firdawsi's Shahnamah, the earlier parts, done for the Ottoman Sultan Osman II (16181622).
- Title (Romanized): [Mev'iza ve K?sas-i enbiya] Title (English): [Admonitions and tales of the prophets], Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 333; 85 leaves: paper; 209 x 147 mm. bound to 209 x 145 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded Brown leather, blind-stamped with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, beginning and ending missing. (Box 71)
  A Turkish tales of the prophet. A provenance date of 24 December 1742 on the inside front cover.
- Title (Romanized): Leylâ ve Mecnûn Title (English): Layli and Majnun Alternative titles: ???? ? ?????, Date: 1824; Manuscript number: 334; 101 leaves: paper; 224 x 113 mm. bound to 224 x 117 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Decorated green paper over boards and fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 71)
  Fuzuli's Turkish version of the romance of Layli and Majnun, firs popularized through the Persian version of Ni?ami Ganjavi (1140 or 41-1202 or 3)
- Title (Romanized): [T?bb] Title (English): [Medicine], Date: 1752 April; Manuscript number: 335; 204 leaves: paper; 213 x 136 mm. no binding.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Missing. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, apparently 38 leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 71)
  Medical treatise on the use of drugs and the curing of various ailments.
- Title (Romanized): [Camiu'l]-mucizat Title (English): [The Collection of] miracles, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 336; 142 leaves: paper; 211 x 131 mm. bound to 209 x 131 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green marble paper over boards with burgundy leather stripe on spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; marginalia; title on bottom edge. (Box 71)
  Form of author's name is from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 417. He is also known as Gülseni Ibrahim Nezira.
  Treatise on varous prophetic miracles.
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 337; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 71)
- Title (Romanized): Huban[name] Uniform title: Hubanname Title (English): [Book of] the Good Alternative titles: Defter-i Ask, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 338; 74 leaves: paper; 210 x 150 mm. bound to 209 x 148 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Red, grey, and yellow marble paper over boards with brown leather stripe on spine, and fore- edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 71)
  A collection of the narrative verse of the Ottoman poet on the beautiful. The volume contains three titles, all told.
- Title (Romanized): Camiu'l-envar fi menakibu'l-ebrar Title (English): Collection of lightrays in the life-tales of the upright people, Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 339; 140 leaves: paper; 223 x 130 mm. bound to 223 x 128 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather with gilt decoration, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap and purple and gilt paste- downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in gilt borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 71)
  A biography of the famous men of aghdad written in 1666/7 for the Ottoman governor of that city Ibrahim Pasa.
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 340; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 71)
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 341; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 71)
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 342; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 72)
- Title (Romanized): [Mecmau'l-letaif] Title (English): [Anthology of pleasant tales] Alternative titles: ???? ???????, Majma` al-la?a'if, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 343; 110 leaves: paper; 204 x 144 mm. bound to 205 x 141 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Soft brown leather, damaged. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, water damage; beginning missing. (Box 72)
  Identification of author and date from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 216, footnote.
  A collection of biblical/Quranic tales composed in the sixteenth century.
- Date: [16--], Manuscript number: 344; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 72)
- Title (Romanized): Ervahname Title (English): Book of spirits Alternative titles: ????? ????, Arva?'namah, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 345; 89 leaves: paper; 207 x 145 mm. bound to 206 x 152 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded green marble paper with dark leather on spine and around the edges, fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, water damage; ending missing. (Box 72)
  But on 1b the author is called Pir Muhiuddin.
  A verse treatise on Sufism, the second title, Sefaatname (beginning on 23b) treats the Sufi master Emir Sultan.
- Title (Romanized): [Hesap] Title (English): [Arithmetics ], Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 346; 96 leaves: paper; 212 x 143 mm. bound to 212 x 138 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded brown leather with dark leather on spine and around the edges, damaged fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, calculations in red, beginning missing. (Box 72)
  A book on basic arithmetics.
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 347; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 72)
- unspecified, Manuscript number: 348; Layout: Script: Decoration: Binding: Additional description: (Box 72)
- Title (Romanized): [Esrarname] Title (English): [Book of secrets] Alternative titles: Asrar'namah, ?????????, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 349; 133 leaves: paper; 217 x 164 mm. bound to 218 x 160 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded blue marble paper with black leather on spine and around the edges. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 72)
  Turkish tanslation of the Persian metrical treatise attributed to the Sufi master Farid al-Din A??ar (d. ca. 1230).
- Title (Romanized): Hayriname Title (English): Book of goodness Alternative titles: Hayriyye, Hari-name, Khayri'namah,???? ????, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 350; 110 leaves: paper; 222 x 157 mm. bound to 221 x 162 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded marble paper with brown leather on spine and and around the edges; fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 72)
  Ethical treatise in verse on a wide variety of topics.